I'd like to take you on the epic quest of the Rosetta spacecraft.
تعالوا معي في هذه الرحلة الأسطورية، على متن المركبة الفضائية "روزيتا".
To escort and land the probe on a comet,
لمرافقة مسبار فضائي والهبوط به على مُذنّب.
this has been my passion for the past two years.
كان هذا شغلي الشاغل طوال العامين الماضيين.
In order to do that,
ومن أجل القيام بذلك،
I need to explain to you something about the origin of the solar system.
أود أن أشرح لكم قليلًا عن نشأة المجموعة الشمسية.
When we go back four and a half billion years,
إذا عدنا 4.5 مليار سنة إلى الوراء،
there was a cloud of gas and dust.
كانت هناك سحابة من الغاز والغبار.
In the center of this cloud, our sun formed and ignited.
في مركز تلك السحابة، تشكلت شمسنا وبدأت بالاشتعال.
What then happened, according to theory,
ووفقًا للنظرية، فإن ما حدث بعد ذلك،
is that when the Earth had cooled down a bit after its formation,
هو أنه عندما بَرَدت الأرض بعد تكوّنها بقليل،
comets massively impacted the Earth and delivered water to Earth.
اصطدمت المذنبات بشكل هائل بالأرض وأوصلت المياه إلى الأرض.
and that may have bootstrapped the emergence of life.
ولعل هذا قد مهّد لنشأة الحياة.
You can compare this to having to solve a 250-piece puzzle
يمكنك أن تقارن هذا بحلك لأحجية من 250 قطعة،
and not a 2,000-piece puzzle.
وليس أحجية مكونة من 2,000 قطعة.
Afterwards, the big planets like Jupiter and Saturn,
بعدئذ، فإن الكواكب الكبيرة مثل المشترى و زحل،
they were not in their place where they are now,
لم تكن في المكان الذي تحتله الآن،
and they interacted gravitationally,
وبفعل جاذبيتها البينيّة،
and they swept the whole interior of the solar system clean,
فقد كنست المحيط الداخلي للنظام الشمسي بأكمله،
and what we now know as comets
وانتهى المطاف يما تُعرف بالمذنبات
ended up in something called the Kuiper Belt,
إلى شيء يسمى بـ "حزام كويبر".
which is a belt of objects beyond the orbit of Neptune.
وهو حزام من الجسيمات يقع خلف مدار نبتون،
And sometimes these objects run into each other,
وأحيانًا تصطدم هذه الأجسام بعضها ببعض،
and they gravitationally deflect,
فينحرف اتجاهها بسبب الجاذبية؛
and then the gravity of Jupiter pulls them back into the solar system.
ومن ثَمّ تسحبها جاذبية المشتري مرة أخرى إلى داخل النظام الشمسي،
And they then become the comets as we see them in the sky.
وهكذا تتحول هذه الأجسام إلى المذنبات التي نراها في السماء.
The important thing here to note is that in the meantime,
الشيء المهم الذي علينا أن نلاحظه، هو أنه بينما مرت
the four and a half billion years,
4.5 مليار سنة،
these comets have been sitting on the outside of the solar system,
كانت هذه المذنبات متمركزة خارج النظام الشمسي،
and haven't changed --
ولم يطرأ عليها أي تغيير.
deep, frozen versions of our solar system.
نُسَخ مُجَمّدة تمامًا من نظامنا الشمسي.
In the sky, they look like this.
وهي تبدو هكذا في السماء.
We know them for their tails.
نعرفها من أذيالها.
There are actually two tails.
في الحقيقة للمذنب ذيلان،
and they follow the magnetic field in the solar system.
وهي تتبع المجال المغناطيسي للنظام الشمسي.
There's the coma,
هذه هي الغُرّة،
and then there is the nucleus, which here is too small to see,
ثم هناك النواة، وهي هنا صغيرة جدًا لتُرى.
and you have to remember that in the case of Rosetta,
وعليك أن تتذكر، أنه في حالة "روزيتا"،
the spacecraft is in that center pixel.
فإن المركبة في منتصف تلك النقطة الدقيقة.
We are only 20, 30, 40 kilometers away from the comet.
فنحن على بعد 20 أو 30 أو 40 كيلومترًا فقط من المذنب.
So what's important to remember?
إذًا، فما الذي ينبغي علينا تذكره؟
Comets contain the original material from which our solar system was formed,
تحتوي المذنبات على المادة الأساسية التي تشكل منها نظامنا الشمسي.
so they're ideal to study the components
لذا فهي مادة مثالية لدراسة المكونات
that were present at the time when Earth, and life, started.
التي كانت حاضرة عندما تشكلت الأرض وبدأت الحياة.
Comets are also suspected
كما يُعتقد أن المذنبات
of having brought the elements which may have bootstrapped life.
قد أحضرت العناصر التي ربما قد مهدت لنشأة الحياة.
In 1983, ESA set up its long-term Horizon 2000 program,
عام 1938، أطلقت وكالة الفضاء الأوروبية برنامج "هورايزون 2000" طويل الأمد،
which contained one cornerstone, which would be a mission to a comet.
الذي اضطلع بمهمة أساسية، وهي مَهَمة إلى مذنب.
In parallel, a small mission to a comet, what you see here, Giotto, was launched,
وبالتوازي، تم إطلاق مهمة صغيرة إلى مذنب، تدعى جيوتو، وهي ما تراه هنا.
and in 1986, flew by the comet of Halley with an armada of other spacecraft.
وفي عام 1986، حلقت المهمة بجانب مذنب هالي برفقة أسطول من المركبات الفضائية الأخرى.
From the results of that mission, it became immediately clear
من نتائج تلك المهمة أنه أصبح جليًّا للعيان،
that comets were ideal bodies to study to understand our solar system.
أن المذنبات كانت هياكل مثالية للدراسة لنفهم نظامنا الشمسي.
And thus, the Rosetta mission was approved in 1993,
وهكذا فإن مهمة "روزيتا" قد تم اعتمادها في عام 1993،
and originally it was supposed to be launched in 2003,
وكان يُفترض أن تُطلق أساسًا عام 2003.
but a problem arose with an Ariane rocket.
لكن ظهرت مشكلة في صاروخ آريان.
However, our P.R. department, in its enthusiasm,
على أي حال، فإن قسم العلاقلات العامة، وفي خضمّ حماسته،
had already made 1,000 Delft Blue plates
كان بالفعل قد صنع 1000 طبق من الفخار الأزرق،
with the name of the wrong comets.
وعليها اسم المذنب الخطأ.
So I've never had to buy any china since. That's the positive part.
وعليه، فلم أضطر لشراء أوانٍ خزفية منذئذٍ. ذاك هو الجانب الإيجابي في الموضوع.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Once the whole problem was solved,
عندما حُلّت المشكلة برُمتها،
we left Earth in 2004
غادرنا الأرض عام 2004،
to the newly selected comet, Churyumov-Gerasimenko.
إلى المذنب الذي اختير من جديد "تشوريوموف-جيراسِمِنكو".
This comet had to be specially selected
وقد توجّب اختيار هذا المذنب بشكل خاص،
because A, you have to be able to get to it,
لأنه، أولًا: عليك أن تكون قادرًا على الوصول إليه؛
and B, it shouldn't have been in the solar system too long.
وثانيًا: ينبغي ألا يكون داخل النظام الشمسي منذ زمن طويل.
This particular comet has been in the solar system since 1959.
هذا المذنب بالذات كان داخل النظام الشمسي منذ عام 1959.
That's the first time when it was deflected by Jupiter,
وكانت تلك هي المرة الأولى التي يؤثر فيه كوكب المشتري ويحرف مساره.
and it got close enough to the sun to start changing.
وأصبح قريبًا من الشمس بما يكفي ليبدأ بالتغير.
So it's a very fresh comet.
وهكذا فإنه مذنب جديد جدًا.
Rosetta made a few historic firsts.
حققت "روزيتا" أكثر من سابقة تاريخية،
It's the first satellite to orbit a comet,
فقد كانت أول قمر اصطناعي يدور حول مذنب،
and to escort it throughout its whole tour through the solar system --
ويرافقه طوال كامل رحلته عبر النظام الشمسي،
closest approach to the sun, as we will see in August,
أثناء أدنى اقتراب له من الشمس كما سنراه في أغسطس،
and then away again to the exterior.
ثم أثناء ابتعاده مرة أخرى إلى الخارج.
It's the first ever landing on a comet.
إنه أول حالة هبوط على مذنب على الإطلاق.
We actually orbit the comet using something which is not
في الحقيقة، فقد قمنا بالدوران حول المذنب باستخدام شيء لا نقوم بفعله عادة
normally done with spacecraft.
باستخدام المركبة الفضائية.
Normally, you look at the sky and you know where you point and where you are.
عادة، تنظر إلى السماء فتدرك إلى أين تشير وأين أنت،
In this case, that's not enough.
في هذه الحالة، ليس ذلك كافيًا.
We navigated by looking at landmarks on the comet.
فقد تنقلنا عن طريق متابعة معالم محددة على سطح المذنب.
We recognized features -- boulders, craters --
ولاحظنا وجود أشياء مثل الصخور والحفر،
and that's how we know where we are respective to the comet.
و هكذا تمكنا من معرفة مكاننا بالنسبة للمذنب.
And, of course, it's the first satellite to go beyond the orbit of Jupiter
و بالطبع كان القمر الاصطناعي الأول الذي يتجاوز مدار كوكب المشتري،
on solar cells.
باستخدام الخلايا الشمسية.
Now, this sounds more heroic than it actually is,
يبدو هذا أكثر بطولة مما هو عليه في الواقع،
because the technology to use radio isotope thermal generators
لأن إمكانية استخدام المولدات الحرارية المشعة
wasn't available in Europe at that time, so there was no choice.
لم تكن متوافرة في أوروبا حينها، لذا لم يكن هناك مجال للاختيار.
But these solar arrays are big.
وألواح الطاقة الشمسية هذه كبيرة .
This is one wing, and these are not specially selected small people.
ذلك جناح واحد، و هؤلاء ليسوا أشخاصًا تم انتقاؤهم خصيصًا.
They're just like you and me.
إنهم مثلك و مثلي.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
We have two of these wings, 65 square meters.
لدينا جناحان كهذا، يمتدان على مساحة 65 متر مربع.
Now later on, of course, when we got to the comet,
بالطبع، بعد ذلك، وعندما وصلنا إلى المذنب،
you find out that 65 square meters of sail
وجدنا أن شراعًا مساحته 65 مترًا مربعًا
close to a body which is outgassing is not always a very handy choice.
ينفث الغاز بالقرب من هيكل ، و هذا لا يمثل دومًا خيارًا صائبًا.
Now, how did we get to the comet?
كيف تمكنّا من الوصول إلى المذنب؟
Because we had to go there for the Rosetta scientific objectives
كان علينا الوصول إلى هناك من أجل الأهداف العلمية للمركبة "روزيتا"،
very far away -- four times the distance of the Earth to the sun --
بعيدًا جدًا، إلى أربعة أضعاف المسافة بين الأرض والشمس؛
and also at a much higher velocity than we could achieve with fuel,
وبسرعة أعلى من تلك التي يمكننا بلوغها باستخدام الوقود.
because we'd have to take six times as much fuel as the whole spacecraft weighed.
إذ كان ليتوجب علينا استخدام وقود يبلغ وزنه ستة أضعاف وزن المركبة.
So what do you do?
ما العمل إذًا؟
You use gravitational flybys, slingshots,
نحلّق باستخدام الجاذبية:
where you pass by a planet at very low altitude,
حيث نطير بالقرب من أحد الكواكب على ارتفاع منخفض جدًا،
a few thousand kilometers,
بضعة آلاف من الكيلومترات،
and then you get the velocity of that planet around the sun for free.
ثم نكتسب سرعة دوران ذلك الكوكب حول الشمس من دون استهلاك للطاقة.
We did that a few times.
لقد قمنا بذلك عدة مرات.
We did Earth, we did Mars, we did twice Earth again,
حول الأرض، والمريخ، ثم حول الأرض لمرتين،
and we also flew by two asteroids, Lutetia and Steins.
كما حلّقنا بالقرب من كويكبين: لوتيشيا وستاينز.
Then in 2011, we got so far from the sun that if the spacecraft got into trouble,
وفي عام 2011، ابتعدنا كثيرًا عن الشمس لدرجة أنه في حال أصاب المركبة عطلٌ ما،
we couldn't actually save the spacecraft anymore,
فإننا لم نكن لنتمكن من إنقاذها.
so we went into hibernation.
لذا، فقد دخلنا في حالة سبات؛
Everything was switched off except for one clock.
قمنا بإغلاق كل شيء، عدا ساعة واحدة.
Here you see in white the trajectory, and the way this works.
باللون الأبيض هنا، ترون مسار المركبة، وكيف تسير الأمور.
You see that from the circle where we started,
كما ترون، ابتداءً من الدائرة حيث انطلقنا،
the white line, actually you get more and more and more elliptical,
مع الخط الأبيض، ترون أن المسار يصبح إهليلجيًا أكثر فأكثر؛
and then finally we approached the comet
إلى أن اقتربنا من المذنب في نهاية المطاف،
in May 2014, and we had to start doing the rendezvous maneuvers.
في مايو 2014، وبات علينا البدء بمناورات الالتحام.
On the way there, we flew by Earth and we took a few pictures to test our cameras.
و في طريقنا ، مررنا بالقرب من الأرض، و التقطنا بعض الصور للتحقق من كاميراتنا.
This is the moon rising over Earth,
ترون هنا القمر يبزغ فوق الأرض.
and this is what we now call a selfie,
وهذه الصورة التي نسميها اليوم "سيلفي"،
which at that time, by the way, that word didn't exist. (Laughter)
وبالمناسبة، لم تكن هذه الكلمة قد اخترعت بعد في ذلك الوقت (ضحك).
It's at Mars. It was taken by the CIVA camera.
التقطت الصورة بالقرب من المريخ باستخدام كاميرا CIVA،
That's one of the cameras on the lander,
وهي إحدى الكاميرات الموجودة على المسبار،
and it just looks under the solar arrays,
تحت الألواح الشمسية مباشرة.
and you see the planet Mars and the solar array in the distance.
وترون هنا كوكب المريخ والألواح الشمسية في عمق الصورة.
Now, when we got out of hibernation in January 2014,
وعندما خرجنا من حالة السبات في يناير 2014،
we started arriving at a distance
كنا نقترب من الوصول إلى مسافة
of two million kilometers from the comet in May.
2 مليون كلم من المذنب في مايو.
However, the velocity the spacecraft had was much too fast.
لكن المركبة حينها كانت تحلق بسرعة عالية جدًا.
We were going 2,800 kilometers an hour faster than the comet, so we had to brake.
فقد كنا نحلق أسرع من المذنب بمقدار2800 كلم/سا،وكان علينا تخفيف سرعتنا.
We had to do eight maneuvers,
توجب علينا القيام بثماني مناورات.
and you see here, some of them were really big.
وكما ترون هنا، كان بعضها ضخمًا بالفعل.
We had to brake the first one by a few hundred kilometers per hour,
قمنا في المرحلة الأولى بتخفيف السرعة لبضع مئات من الكيلومترات في الساعة فقط؛
and actually, the duration of that was seven hours,
واستغرق ذلك سبع ساعات،
and it used 218 kilos of fuel,
واستهلك 218 كغ من الوقود.
and those were seven nerve-wracking hours, because in 2007,
لقد كانت تلك الساعات السبع مرهقة جدًا، ففي عام 2007،
there was a leak in the system of the propulsion of Rosetta,
كان ثمة تسرب في نظام الدفع في روزيتا؛
and we had to close off a branch,
وتوجّب علينا إغلاق فرع بالكامل،
so the system was actually operating at a pressure
لذا فقد كان النظام يعمل تحت مستوى من الضغط
which it was never designed or qualified for.
لم يكن مصممًا أو مؤهلًا له.
Then we got in the vicinity of the comet, and these were the first pictures we saw.
ثم اقتربنا من المذنب، وكانت هذه أولى الصور التي رأيناها.
The true comet rotation period is 12 and a half hours,
كانت مدة دوران المذنب الفعلية تبلغ 12 و 1/2 الساعة.
so this is accelerated,
هذه صورة مسرّعة إذًا.
but you will understand that our flight dynamics engineers thought,
وأنتم تدركون الآن أن خبراء الهندسة الدينامية في رحلتنا،
this is not going to be an easy thing to land on.
اعتقدوا أن مهمة الهبوط على المذنب لن تكون سهلة.
We had hoped for some kind of spud-like thing
وكنا نأمل أن نجد شيئًا مسطحًا نسبيًا،
where you could easily land.
بحيث يمكننا الهبوط عليه بسهولة.
But we had one hope: maybe it was smooth.
كان يحدونا أمل بأن يكون سطحه أملس.
No. That didn't work either. (Laughter)
ولكن لا، لم يكن الأمر كذلك (ضحك).
So at that point in time, it was clearly unavoidable:
إذّا، في تلك المرحلة، كان الأمر حتميًّا:
we had to map this body in all the detail you could get,
كان علينا وضع خريطة تفصيلية قدر الإمكان للمذنب.
because we had to find an area which is 500 meters in diameter and flat.
إذ كان علينا أن نجد مساحة مسطّحة يبلغ قطرها 500 متر.
Why 500 meters? That's the error we have on landing the probe.
لماذا 500 متر؟ كان ذلك هو هامش الخطأ لعملية هبوط المسبار.
So we went through this process, and we mapped the comet.
شرعنا في القيام بهذه العملية، وقمنا بوضع خريطة للمذنب
We used a technique called photoclinometry.
باستخدام تقنية تسمى "الرسم باستحدام الضوء".
You use shadows thrown by the sun.
حيث نستفيد من الظلال الناجمة عن ضوء الشمس.
What you see here is a rock sitting on the surface of the comet,
ما ترونه هنا هو صخرة على سطح المذنب،
and the sun shines from above.
حيث تسطع الشمس من الأعلى.
From the shadow, we, with our brain,
ومن خلال الظل، وباستخدام عقولنا،
can immediately determine roughly what the shape of that rock is.
يمكننا على الفور تحديد الشكل التقريبي للصخرة.
You can program that in a computer,
ويمكننا برمجة هذه الطريقة على الحاسوب،
you then cover the whole comet, and you can map the comet.
ومن ثم نقوم بتغطية المذنب بالكامل، لنحصل على خريطة تفصيلية له.
For that, we flew special trajectories starting in August.
ومن أجل القيام ذلك، قمنا بالتحليق على مسارات محددة بدءًا من أغسطس.
First, a triangle of 100 kilometers on a side
أولًا، على مثلث بطول 100 كلم؛
at 100 kilometers' distance,
وعلى بعد 100 كلم؛
and we repeated the whole thing at 50 kilometers.
ثم قمنا بالعملية برمتها ثانيةً على بعد 50 كلم.
At that time, we had seen the comet at all kinds of angles,
عندها، تمكنّا من تكوين صورة كاملة للمذنب من كافة جوانبه.
and we could use this technique to map the whole thing.
واستخدمنا هذه الطريقة لرسم خريطة متكاملة للمذنب.
Now, this led to a selection of landing sites.
وقادنا ذلك للعثور على عدة مواقع محتملة للهبوط.
This whole process we had to do, to go from the mapping of the comet
وقد استغرقت هذه العملية برمتها، بدءًا برسم خريطة للمذنب،
to actually finding the final landing site, was 60 days.
وانتهاءً بتحديد موقع الهبوط بشكل نهائي، استغرقت 60 يومًا.
We didn't have more.
لم يكن أمامنا سعة من الوقت.
To give you an idea, the average Mars mission
ولكي أضعكم في الصورة،
takes hundreds of scientists for years to meet
تستغرق المهمة إلى المريخ سنوات من الوقت واجتماع مئات من العلماء،
about where shall we go?
لتحديد الوجهة النهائية.
We had 60 days, and that was it.
وقد كان أمامنا 60 يومًا فقط.
We finally selected the final landing site
قمنا أخيرًا بتحديد موقع الهبوط بشكل نهائي،
and the commands were prepared for Rosetta to launch Philae.
وتم إعداد "روزيتا" لإطلاق "فيلاي".
The way this works is that Rosetta has to be at the right point in space,
ولكي ينجح الأمر، كان على "روزيتا" أن تكون في الموقع الصحيح بالضبط،
and aiming towards the comet, because the lander is passive.
وموجّهة نحو المذنب، إذ أن المسبار يعمل بصورة سلبية.
The lander is then pushed out and moves towards the comet.
بعدئذ، يتم دفع المسبار خارجًا باتجاه المذنب.
Rosetta had to turn around
وكان على "روزيتا" الاستدارة،
to get its cameras to actually look at Philae while it was departing
بحيث تتوجه الكاميرات نحو "فيلاي" أثناء مغادرته المركبة،
and to be able to communicate with it.
وبحيث نستطيع التواصل معه.
Now, the landing duration of the whole trajectory was seven hours.
استغرقت عملية الهبوط لكامل المسار 7 ساعات.
Now do a simple calculation:
لنقم بعملية حسابية بسيطة:
if the velocity of Rosetta is off by one centimeter per second,
لو حدث خطأ في سرعة "روزيتا" بمقدارسنتيمتر واحد في الثانية،
seven hours is 25,000 seconds.
ونعلم أن 7 ساعات تساوي 25 ألف ثانية،
That means 252 meters wrong on the comet.
فإن ذلك يعني أن يحيد المسبار عن موقع هبوطه 252 مترًا.
So we had to know the velocity of Rosetta
لذا فقد توجب علينا معرفة سرعة "روزيتا"
much better than one centimeter per second,
بدقة تفوق سنتيمترًا واحدًا في الثانية،
and its location in space better than 100 meters
ومعرفة موقعها في الفضاء بدقة تفوق 100 متر.
at 500 million kilometers from Earth.
كل ذلك على بعد 500 مليون كلم من الأرض.
That's no mean feat.
إن ذلك لإنجاز جبار.
Let me quickly take you through some of the science and the instruments.
دعوني أوجز لكم بعض المعارف والأدوات المستخدمة هنا.
I won't bore you with all the details of all the instruments,
لن أصدع رؤوسكم بكافة التفاصيل المتعلقة بالأدوات.
but it's got everything.
لنقل إنها مجهزة بكل شيء.
We can sniff gas, we can measure dust particles,
فقد كنا نستطيع سحب الغازات، وقياس أبعاد جزيئات الغبار،
the shape of them, the composition,
وشكلها، وتركيبها؛
there are magnetometers, everything.
كما ضمّت أدوات لقياس المغناطيسية، كان لدينا كل شيء.
This is one of the results from an instrument which measures gas density
ههنا إحدى النتائج التي توصلنا إليها من إحدى الأدوات التي تقيس كثافة الغازات،
at the position of Rosetta,
من موقع "روزيتا".
so it's gas which has left the comet.
هذا هو الغاز الذي صدر عن المذنب؛
The bottom graph is September of last year.
يمثل الشكل السفلي شهر سبتمبر من العام الماضي.
There is a long-term variation, which in itself is not surprising,
ثمة انحراف واضح على المدى الطويل، وهو أمر غير مفاجئ بحد ذاته؛
but you see the sharp peaks.
ولكن هل ترون هذه القمم الحادة؟
This is a comet day.
تمثل كلٌ منها يومًا من عمر المذنب.
You can see the effect of the sun on the evaporation of gas
يمكنكم رؤية تأثير الشمس على عملية تبخر الغازات.
and the fact that the comet is rotating.
وبالنظر إلى أن المذنب يدور،
So there is one spot, apparently,
فمن الواضح أن هناك بقعة محددة
where there is a lot of stuff coming from,
تخرج منها كل هذه الأشياء؛
it gets heated in the Sun, and then cools down on the back side.
حيث تسخن تحت تأثير الشمس، ومن ثم تبرد عندما تصبح على الجانب الآخر.
And we can see the density variations of this.
ويمكننا هنا رؤية التغيرات الحاصلة في كثافة الغاز.
These are the gases and the organic compounds
هذه قائمة بالغازات والمكونات العضوية
that we already have measured.
التي استطعنا قياسها بالفعل.
You will see it's an impressive list,
وكما ترون فهي قائمة غنية ومثيرة،
and there is much, much, much more to come,
ولا يزال هناك الكثير الكثير مما سنكتشفه،
because there are more measurements.
حيث سنقوم بالمزيد من القياسات.
Actually, there is a conference going on in Houston at the moment
في الواقع، هناك مؤتمر تجري أحداثه في هيوستن في هذه اللحظات،
where many of these results are presented.
حيث يتم عرض الكثير من هذه النتائج.
Also, we measured dust particles.
و لقد قسنا أيضًا جزيئات الغبار؛
Now, for you, this will not look very impressive,
قد لا يبدو لكم ذلك بالأمر المهم،
but the scientists were thrilled when they saw this.
لكن العلماء ذهلوا عندما رأوا هذا:
Two dust particles:
جزيئتان من الغبار:
the right one they call Boris, and they shot it with tantalum
أطلقوا على الجزيئة اليمنى اسم بوريس، وعالجوها باستخدام التنتالوم
in order to be able to analyze it.
لكي يتمكنوا من تحليلها.
Now, we found sodium and magnesium.
وقد وجدنا الصوديوم والمغنيزيوم.
What this tells you is this is the concentration of these two materials
يشير ذلك إلى أن هذا ما كان عليه تركيز هاتين المادتين
at the time the solar system was formed,
عند تشكّل نظامنا الشمسي.
so we learned things about which materials were there
وهكذا فقد عرفنا ما المواد التي كانت موجودة
when the planet was made.
عندما تشكل كوكبنا.
Of course, one of the important elements is the imaging.
بالطبع، كان التصوير عاملًا بالغ الأهمية.
This is one of the cameras of Rosetta, the OSIRIS camera,
هذه إحدى الكاميرات الموجودة على روزيتا. كاميرا أوزيريس؛
and this actually was the cover of Science magazine
وقد احتلت هذه الصورة غلاف مجلة العلوم
on January 23 of this year.
يوم 23 يناير من هذا العام.
Nobody had expected this body to look like this.
لم يكن أحدٌ يتوقع أن يكون الجرم بهذا الشكل؛
Boulders, rocks -- if anything, it looks more like the Half Dome in Yosemite
فقد كانت معالم الصخور تشبه إلى حد بعيد
than anything else.
صخرة "هاف دوم" في يوزيميتي.
We also saw things like this:
كما شاهدنا أيضًا أشياء كهذه:
dunes, and what look to be, on the righthand side, wind-blown shadows.
كثبانًا رملية، وكما يبدو إلى يمين الصورة، ظلال أحدثتها الرياح.
Now we know these from Mars, but this comet doesn't have an atmosphere,
لقد شاهدنا ذلك من قبل على المريخ، لكن هذا المذنب لا يمتلك غلافًا جويًا؛
so it's a bit difficult to create a wind-blown shadow.
لذا فإن من الصعب تشكّل ظلال بفعل الرياح.
It may be local outgassing,
قد يكون ذلك بسبب تفريغ غازات محلية.
stuff which goes up and comes back.
أي أشياء تصعد وتهبط ثانية.
We don't know, so there is a lot to investigate.
نحن لا نعلم بالضبط، لذا فإننا بحاجة للمزيد من البحث.
Here, you see the same image twice.
ترون هنا الصورة ذاتها مرتين.
On the left-hand side, you see in the middle a pit.
إلى اليسار، ترون حفرة في الوسط.
On the right-hand side, if you carefully look,
إلى اليمين، وإذا أمعنتم النظر،
there are three jets coming out of the bottom of that pit.
ترون ثلاثة اندفاعات غازية تخرج من أسفل الحفرة،
So this is the activity of the comet.
وذلك بسبب نشاط المذنب.
Apparently, at the bottom of these pits is where the active regions are,
كانت المناطق النشطة،على ما يبدو في أسفل تلك الحفر،
and where the material evaporates into space.
حيث تتبخر المواد وتنطلق في الفضاء.
There is a very intriguing crack in the neck of the comet.
ثمة شق غريب ومثير للاهتمام عند عنق المذنب؛
You see it on the right-hand side.
بإمكانك رؤيته إلى الجانب الأيمن.
It's a kilometer long, and it's two and a half meters wide.
يبلغ طوله كيلومترًا واحدًا، وعرضه مترين ونصف.
Some people suggest that actually,
يقترح البعض،
when we get close to the sun,
أنه عند اقترابه من الشمس،
the comet may split in two,
فإن المذنب قد ينشطر إلى قسمين،
and then we'll have to choose,
وعندها يستوجب علينا الاختيار،
which comet do we go for?
أي المذنبين سنختار؟
The lander -- again, lots of instruments,
عودة إلى المسبار.-- ومعداته الكثيرة.
mostly comparable except for the things which hammer in the ground and drill, etc.
فعدا المعدات المسؤولة عن الحفر والطَرق،
But much the same as Rosetta, and that is because you want to compare
يمكن مقارنة المسبار بروزيتا، إذ أننا نريد المقارنة،
what you find in space with what you find on the comet.
بين ما نجده في الفضاء، وما وجدناه على المذنب.
These are called ground truth measurements.
وتسمى هذه القياسات: القياسات الحقيقة على الأرض.
These are the landing descent images
ترون هنا صور عملية الهبوط،
that were taken by the OSIRIS camera.
التي التقطت بواسطة كاميرا أوزيريس.
You see the lander getting further and further away from Rosetta.
وترون كيف يبتعد المسبار شيئًا فشيئًا عن روزيتا.
On the top right, you see an image taken at 60 meters by the lander,
أعلى ويمين الشاشة، ترون صورة التقطها المسبار على ارتفاع 60 مترًا،
60 meters above the surface of the comet.
60 مترًا من سطح المذنب.
The boulder there is some 10 meters.
تبلغ أبعاد الصخور هنا نحو عشرة أمتار،
So this is one of the last images we took before we landed on the comet.
وكانت هذه إحدى آخر الصور التي التقطناها قبل أن نحط على سطح المذنب.
Here, you see the whole sequence again, but from a different perspective,
ترون هنا سلسلة الصور مرة أخرى، ولكن من زاوية أخرى.
and you see three blown-ups from the bottom-left to the middle
وترون ثلاثة اندفاعات من أسفل ويسار الشاشة إلى الوسط،
of the lander traveling over the surface of the comet.
للمسبار وهو يحلق فوق سطح المذنب.
Then, at the top, there is a before and an after image of the landing.
و في أعلى الشاشة، هناك صورتان، قبل وبعد عملية الهبوط.
The only problem with the after image is, there is no lander.
المشكلة الوحيدة لصورة ما بعد الهبوط هي عدم وجود المسبار فيها.
But if you carefully look at the right-hand side of this image,
ولكن إذا أمعنتم النظر في يمين الصورة،
we saw the lander still there, but it had bounced.
فسترون أن المسبار ما زال هناك، غير أنه ارتد إلى الأعلى،
It had departed again.
وغادر سطح المذنب ثانيةً.
Now, on a bit of a comical note here
المفارقة الطريفة هنا،
is that originally Rosetta was designed to have a lander which would bounce.
أن مركبة روزيتا كانت مصممةً بالأصل بحيث تحمل مسبارًا يمكنه الارتداد،
That was discarded because it was way too expensive.
لكننا تخلّينا عن تلك الفكرة بسبب تكلفتها العالية.
Now, we forgot, but the lander knew.
حسنًا، لقد نسينا ، لكن المسبار لم ينسَ.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
During the first bounce, in the magnetometers,
أثناء القفزة الأولى، وكما نرى في المقياس؛
you see here the data from them, from the three axes, x, y and z.
يعطينا الشكل معلومات عن المحاور الثلاثة: س، ع، ص
Halfway through, you see a red line.
وفي المنتصف، هناك خط أحمر.
At that red line, there is a change.
عند الخط الأحمر، هناك تغيير.
What happened, apparently, is during the first bounce,
يبدو أن ما حصل أثناء القفزة الأولى،
somewhere, we hit the edge of a crater with one of the legs of the lander,
هو أننا اصطدمنا بحافة الفوهة بأحد أذرع المسبار،
and the rotation velocity of the lander changed.
فتغيرت بذلك سرعة دوران المسبار.
So we've been rather lucky
لقد كنا محظوظين إذًا،
that we are where we are.
بكوننا في ذلك الموقع.
This is one of the iconic images of Rosetta.
هذه إحدى أهم الصور التي التقطتها روزيتا،
It's a man-made object, a leg of the lander,
فهي تصور جسمًا من صنع الإنسان، وهو ذراع المسبار،
standing on a comet.
يحط على سطح مذنب.
This, for me, is one of the very best images of space science I have ever seen.
بالنسبة لي، تمثل هذه إحدى أعظم صور الفضاء على الإطلاق.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
One of the things we still have to do is to actually find the lander.
ما زال يتوجب علينا العثور على المسبار.
The blue area here is where we know it must be.
نعتقد أنه يجب أن يكون ضمن هذه المنطقة الزرقاء؛
We haven't been able to find it yet, but the search is continuing,
لم نتمكن من العثور عليه بعد، لكن البحث لا يزال مستمرًا.
as are our efforts to start getting the lander to work again.
كما نواصل مساعينا لإعادة تشغيل المسبار ثانية،
We listen every day,
فنحن نسمع كل يوم،
and we hope that between now and somewhere in April,
ونأمل أنه في وقت ما بين اليوم وشهر أبريل،
the lander will wake up again.
سوف يستيقظ المسبار من سباته.
The findings of what we found on the comet:
ألخص لكم هنا النتائج بشأن المذنب:
This thing would float in water.
هذا المذنب يطفو على الماء.
It's half the density of water.
فكثافته تبلغ نصف كثافة الماء.
So it looks like a very big rock, but it's not.
إنه يبدو كصخرة هائلة، لكنه ليس كذلك.
The activity increase we saw in June, July, August last year
فنسبة الزيادة في نشاط المذنب، والتي شهدناها في يونيو ويوليو وأغسطس
was a four-fold activity increase.
تبلغ أربعة أضعاف.
By the time we will be at the sun,
وبحلول وقت وصول المذنب إلى الشمس،
there will be 100 kilos a second leaving this comet:
سينجم عن نشاط المذنب خروج 100 كغ في الثانية
gas, dust, whatever.
من الغاز والغبار وغيرها.
That's 100 million kilos a day.
أي ما يصل إلى 100 مليون كغ في اليوم.
Then, finally, the landing day.
وأخيرًا، نصل إلى يوم الهبوط.
I will never forget -- absolute madness, 250 TV crews in Germany.
لن أنسى ذلك ما حييت-- فقد قامت الدنيا ولم تقعد. 250 طاقمًا تلفزيونيًا في ألمانيا.
The BBC was interviewing me,
كانت قناة BBC تجري معي لقاء،
and another TV crew who was following me all day
وطاقم تلفزيوني آخر يلاحقني طوال النهار،
were filming me being interviewed,
ويصورني أثناء المقابلة،
and it went on like that for the whole day.
واستمر ذلك النهار بطوله.
The Discovery Channel crew
أما طاقم قناة ديسكفري،
actually caught me when leaving the control room,
فقد استوقفني عند مغادرتي غرفة المراقبة؛
and they asked the right question,
وطرحوا علي ذلك السؤال.
and man, I got into tears, and I still feel this.
اغرورقت عيناي بالدموع، ومازلت أشعر بالإحساس ذاته.
For a month and a half,
فلمدة شهر ونصف،
I couldn't think about landing day without crying,
لم يخطر ببالي الهبوط من دون أن أبكي،
and I still have the emotion in me.
وما زال هذا الشعور يتملّكني.
With this image of the comet, I would like to leave you.
أما الآن، فأود أن أترككم مع هذه الصورة للمذنب، وأودعكم.
Thank you.
شكرًا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)